# Shivi Gupta

**☎** (+91) 9654689691 • **☒** shivigup@iitk.ac.in • **७** shivigup.github.io

shivigup
shivigup

# **Profile Summary & Research Interests**

I am a senior undergraduate interested in Applied Machine Learning, Computational Physics and Signal Processing. Through research and industrial projects, I have experience in diverse fields such as Computer Vision, Edge Computing, Image & Audio Signal Processing and Control Systems.

## **Education**

## Indian Institute of Technology, Kanpur, India

August 2018 – Present

Double Major BT-BS student - 9.2/10.0

Electrical Engineering with double major in Physics

Minor degree in English Literature

## Technical Skills

Languages: C/C++, Python, MATLAB, JavaScript

Software & Tools: TensorFlow, PyTorch, Keras, NumPy/SciPy, scikit-learn, Pandas, Librosa, jsPsych,

PsyToolkit, Git, HTML/CSS, Wolfram Mathematica, MATLAB

# Research Experience

#### Research Intern | Inter University Accelerator Center, Delhi

December 2021 - Present

Computational Analysis of Tandem Accelerator Parameters for Stable Pulsed Beam Operation Supervisor: Dr. Bhuban Sahu, Research Scientist, IUAC

- Processed data collected over a few months of operation to find beam parameters with high correlations
- Created a deep learning model for the control of the the beam phase
- Presently working on optimizing the model and deploying it for practical use

## **Sunspots Prediction Using Machine Learning Methods**

August 2021 - Present

Undergraduate Project

Supervisor: Prof. Mahendra K Verma, Department of Physics, IIT Kanpur

- Analysed the trends and seasonality of the SILSO sunspots dataset and created prediction models
- Presently trying for better accuracy and preparing a draft for journal publication

**Presentation Slides** 

#### Research Intern | Adobe Research India

May 2021 - August 2021

Designing User Profiles using Edge Computing

Supervisors: Atanu Sinha, Sunav Choudhary, Adobe Research Labs

- Worked in a team on the domain of Edge Computing to bring user profiles from Cloud to Edge
- Incorporated user behaviours to infer preferences across various services to create user representations
- Employed Sequence Modelling, Deep Learning and Multitask Learning techniques
- Various evaluations around compression and updatability were undertaken

#### **Emotion-Color Association in Biologically Inspired DNNs**

August 2020 - January 2021

Undergraduate Project

Supervisor: Prof. K S Venkatesh, Department of Electrical Engineering, IIT Kanpur

- Designed a psychophysical experiment to collect data for choosing colors for a given image
- Showed inherent correlations between images and colors learned by pre-trained image classification neural

Accepted in the Cognitive Science Society 2021 Conference as a poster presentation Abstract in CogSci 2021 | ArXiv preprint | Code

#### Research Intern | SURGE, IIT Kanpur

June 2020 - September 2020

Simulating and Studying Photonic Crystals using the FDTD Method

Supervisor: Dr. Shilpi Gupta, Department of Electrical Engineering, IIT Kanpur

- Studied the finite difference time domain method, used in Ansys Lumerical to simulate optical devices.
- Simulated devices such as photonic crystals, waveguides and grating couplers.
- Studied transmission and reflection for different variations of the devices

Report | Video Presentation | Presentation Slides

# **Projects**

## **Spectrogram Analysis of the Doppler Effect**

August 2021 - November 2021

Course Project in PHY315: Modern Physics Laboratory

Supervisor: Dr. Anjan Kumar Gupta, Department of Physics, IIT Kanpur

- Recorded oscillatory sound profiles for different cases of source and observer movement
- Analysed the spectrograms to find the speed of oscillations, frequency variations and speed of sound

#### Report | Code

#### **Audio Tagging and Sound Event Detection**

August 2021 - November 2021

Course Project in EE603: Machine Learning for Signal Processing

Supervisor: Prof. Vipul Arora, Department of Electrical Engineering, IIT Kanpur

- o Created Machine Learning models to identify presence of music, speech or neither in noisy audio files
- o Further estimated their onset and offset times using signal processing concepts

#### Report | Code

#### **Analysing Brain and CNN Perceptions of Images and Colors**

May 2021 – July 2021

Project mentored under Brain and Cognitive Science Society, IIT Kanpur

- Mentored a group of 7 students to study image encodings of convolutional neural networks
- o Studied a Computer Vision based Python toolbox, DNNBrain and extended it to color inputs
- Designed classifier models to classify colors into hue-based bins

#### Report

## **Relevant Courses**

**Computer Science & Mathematics:** Fundamentals of Computing, Data Structures and Algorithms, High Performance Computing and Machine Learning (ongoing), Linear Algebra, ODE & PDE, Probability and Statistics

**Signal Processing:** Signals, Systems & Networks, Control Systems Analysis, Principles of Communication, Machine Learning for Signal Processing

**Physics:** Quantum Physics, Numerical Methods in Physics, Computational Physics, Classical Mechanics, Modern Physics laboratory, Experimental Physics laboratory (ongoing)

# **Leadership and Activities**

#### **Career Development Mentor**

August 2021 – Present

Academics and Career Council, IIT Kanpur

## Manager, English Literary Events

June 2019 - October 2019

Antaragni 2019, IIT Kanpur

#### Head, Unmukt

June 2019 - May 2020

Community Welfare Cell, IIT Kanpur

#### Secretary, English Literary Society

June 2019 – June 2020

IIT Kanpur